JOHN GUTTAG: Hello again.
This is John Guttag welcoming you back to another exciting segment in 600X.
We ended the last segment looking at ways in which we can use the standard
deviation of a normal distribution to construct confidence
intervals and levels.
We observed that normal distributions are quite common.
If we were to plot the heights of all the students in 600, or for that
matter, the people in this large stadium, we would almost surely
produce something close to a normal distribution.
If one looks at the experimental errors in repeated trials of an
experiment, they are typically normally distributed around zero.
I guess, around zero if the experiment's well-conducted.
Otherwise, the mean is less obvious.
If I plot the average temperatures for almost any place in the world--
this happens to be in the United States--
it will be close to normally distributed as well.
It is important to remember, however, that not all distributions are normal.
Consider rolling a single die.
As we've talked about before, perhaps more than you enjoyed, each of the six
outcomes is equally probable.
If one were to roll a single die a million times and create a histogram
showing how often each number came up, each column will be
almost the same height.
If one were to plot the probability of each possible lottery number being
chosen, it too would be a flat line at one divided by the range of the
lottery numbers.
As we've discussed before, such distributions are called uniform.
Uniform distributions occur frequently in games devised by humans but only
rarely in nature, and are not usually useful for modeling complex systems.
They can be easily characterized by single parameter--
their range.
In contrast to uniform distributions, exponential
distributions occur quite commonly.
They're often, for example, used to model inter-arrival times--
the frequency with which autos enter a highway, or with
web pages are requested.
They're important because they're the only continuous distribution that has
the memoryless property.
What happens at one stage of the distribution is independent of what
happens at other stages.
Consider, for example, the concentration of a drug, and let's
assume it's a legal drug, in the human body.
We start with some finite number of molecules of the drug.
The body's natural instinct is to try and eliminate foreign substances.
So let's assume that at each time step each molecule has a probability, p, of
being cleared.
That is to say, eliminated from the body.
The system is memoryless in the sense that at each time step the probability
of a molecule being cleared is independent of what happened at
previous times.
Let's start at time t equals 0, and ask whether a molecule that was in the
body at time t equals 0 still is.
Well, of course it is, so the probability of that molecule still
being there before any time has elapsed is 1.
How about time t equals 1?
Well, we know that the probability of the molecule being cleared is p, so
the probability of it still being in the body has got to be 1 minus p.
At t equals 2, the probability of that individual molecule still being there
will be 1 minus p squared.
And more generally, at time t equals k, it will be 1 minus p to the k.
Notice, by the way, that this term could be written as 1 minus p to the
1, and this term could even be written as 1 minus p to the 0.
So indeed, we see this formula is correct at each time step.
Now let's suppose that at time t equals 0, there m 0 molecules in the
body to start with.
In general, at time t, the number of molecules still in the body will be m
sub 0 multiplied what?
By the probability that an individual molecule has survived.
And that is the probability we just looked at.
Let's look at some code that implements this to compute how many
molecules are likely to be in the body at any point in time.
The function clear has three arguments--
n, the initial number of molecules, the probability of a molecule being
clear at each step, and the number of steps.
We start by initialize numRemaining to n, so at time t equals
0, there are n molecules.
Then for each step, we append to numRemaining the value of the formula
we just looked at.
And then when we're done, we just plot it all.
We can now look at the code in the code window.
It looks like I've added labels for the x- and y-axes,
that's a good thing.
Now let's run it for 1,000 initial molecules, clearance probability of
0.01, and 500 steps.
Well, we get this rather elegant exponential graph.
This is an example of exponential decay.
In practice, exponential decay is often talked
about in terms of half-life.
Half-life is the expected time required for the initial value to
decay by 50%.
For example, the half-life of a single radioactive atom is a time at which
the probability of that atom having decayed is 0.5.
What you think will happen if I go back to the code and make the y-axis
logarithmic?
Well, that beautiful exponential decay has been replaced by a straight line.
Are you surprised?
Well, you shouldn't be, because recall that the values in the y-axis were
changing at an exponential rate.
That's why it's exponential decay.
And when we make the y-axis logarithmic, the labels on the y-axis
are now also changing at an exponential rate, hence
the straight line.
This is one way to check, by the way, if distributions are exponential.
Notice, by the way, that this code is not a Monte Carlo simulation.
Even though I'm using a probability in this statement, there is no randomness
in this code.
Suppose I want to write a Monte Carlo simulation to test the same thing.
Well, let's go look at that.
ClearSim takes the same three arguments as clear, and again, begins
by initializing numRemaining in the same way, and iterating
through each step.
For each step, it looks at each molecule, m, and either clears it or
not, depending upon whether random.random returns a value less
than, or equal to the clear probability.
Then when it's done, it plots it.
The code down here first runs clear, and then clearSim, so we'll now see in
a single plot the results of both ways of computing the exponential decay.
Notice that these two approaches give us almost identical curves.
That's a good thing.
I would have been worried if they hadn't.
I also would have been worried, by the way, if they'd been identical since,
for one, the simulation, there is some randomness.
So I wouldn't expect it to exactly track the initial values, the
theoretical values given by the blue curve.
And in particular, as the numbers get smaller as we've gone through more
steps, I might expect more divergence because the law of large numbers would
no longer be applicable.
So to get a precise answer, it's better to calculate it from the
probabilities.
On the other hand, the simulation does have some value.
Suppose, for example, I want to change it a little bit.
In fact, let's do something a little bit strange.
Let's assume that this drug is maybe not a drug, but say,
a virus or a bacteria.
Some kind of life form that can reproduce itself.
And so let's modify this simulation to account for the fact that every 100
steps, each of the surviving molecules clones itself.
It can do that quite easily.
Let's put the code in here.
If we're not at the first step, and the step we're at is evenly divisible
by 100, we'll change the number of molecules left to be doubled, numLeft
plus equal numLeft.
And then we'll go off and see what we get there.
Well, here we see that the blue curve is, of course, unchanged, but the red
curves, the simulation, is rather strange.
It drops down until it reaches 100 steps, then it jumps up, drops down.
But we see that it gets smaller and smaller, and we are getting ragged
decay, but effectively, it is still dropping exponentially.
Kind of the fun thing you can do with simulations is try different kinds of
experiments.
Exponential growth is the inverse of exponential decay.
It, too, is quite commonly seen in nature.
Compound interest is an example of exponential growth, as is the growth
of algae in a pond or a swimming pool.
And the power of an atomic bomb is based upon the fact that the energy
grows exponentially.